one thing that I've been thinking about
is the notion of going too tight or too
loose um and it seems to me that it's
more
that like too tight it's not like you're
on one spectrum and you're just too
tight or too
loose if you're too tight that means
that you're going to be too loose where
you should be tighter and you're too
tight where um well you should be
looser but then it will be the case that
like if it's too
much there's something that you're not
seeing that you should be restraining
and everything else is just kind of
secondary to
that well yes yeah yeah um what is it
then that you wouldn't be
seeing if somebody's restraining too
much what is it that they are
overlooking your uh I guess your
incessant tendency to keep saying no
other things yeah so you're giving into
that you should really restrain that
restrain your giving into that to that
mental pressure to double down and say
no to more things just because it's it's
pressuring that
way so that's what's being overlooked as
a result of that one is restraining too
much saying no to stuff that that has
nothing to do with um anything un
wholesome really your criteria well it's still
really your criteria well it's still
going to be just this doesn't feel nice
so if I try harder then I'll feel better
about myself
Well yeah if I if I stick to this long
enough this not feeling nice will go
away but it's
like it would go away either
way as an Arison mental pressure state
it will go
away um so you want to recognize okay
why it has Arison is it because
something I've done or something like no
there's just a mental tendency to okay
the more
uh if there is like if I say no to more
things the quicker it will be quicker
what What will what will be quicker oh
my running away from suffering will be
quicker it's like well the whole
practice is about not being moved by it
not being faster than
it not making it disappear as quickly as
possible which means I want it to go
away the attitude is I don't want this I
crave against it let me do these
practices they will uh remove it for me
that's another thing that I was thinking
about along those lines is I was always
kind of
like console myself with like oh well at
least I have you know a sense of Shame
you know I'm like always trying to be
better and improved but realizing that's
one of
the um
Ides that's one of the like spiritual
powers of the noble
disciples unless you're at that point
you don't have the criteria to
distinguish between well basically you're going to
between well basically you're going to
be feeling guilty about things you
shouldn't be and you're not going to be
feeling guilty about things you
should um and mistaking that for like
actual sense of Shame yeah I think that
can be well that's it's um that kind of
irrational side of the mind that would
feel guilty in regard to things you
shouldn't feel guilty and not feel
guilty in regard things you should feel
guilty it's going to come up that's the
kind of the main trait of an anti mind
and it comes up once you take on The
Virtue take on the sense of strength
start dwelling in
solitudes so it's it's unavoidable it's
not like well this shouldn't be coming
or I could if I do something right this
won't be coming up no that is the the
the the pretty much the main
characteristic of an untain mind is this
irrational placements of emphasis wrong
emphasis on wrong things so it takes
time to undo that so that's why it's
important how you go about
it in that sense so you have that say
irrational guilt you feel guilty on the kind of
guilt you feel guilty on the kind of
stuff that's like not really un
wholesome not even your fault in that
sense but it doesn't diminish the fact
that the mind is resisting it and that's
what that's the guilt that you feel it's
that blind
uh resistance of an untrained mind so
then what do you
do when that happens what do you do when
you're going through those things do you
double down do you tighten the
restraint increase more it's like yeah
but why I I haven't done anything wrong
to begin
with like I am keeping the virtue I am
restrained I am not giving to Wholesome
Behavior yet the Mind still acts like
this why do I need to do anything like
why do I need to tighten more and then
why oh because I don't want this I
resist this so it's kind of like as I
said before you're trying to train a dog
that is
unruly and you are angry at that
unruliness you're upset by it you're
frustrated by it so then it's
like you're not training a dog anymore
you're just trying to get rid of that
unruliness pretty much by any means
necessary because that becomes the focus
of B
that it's like no you have to
acknowledge that the dog is wild that
the mind is
unruly and to tame well exactly that
you're supposed to tame it not like um
conquer it in that sense of just just
force it down until it listens to you
because you w and even if you succeed in
like pinning it
down well you can't hold it forever so
when you unpin it it's going to go back
to its wild ways cuz he still hasn't
really you haven't been communicating
with it there is no there is no
um instruction sort of taking place
there is no conveying of the message to
that mind so yeah sure sometimes it's like
mind so yeah sure sometimes it's like
really unruly you have to just pin it
down yeah of course but I think more
often than not that's not the case it's
more like it's unruly you're frustrated
it's unpleasant you don't want to be
facing that unpleasantness of having to
experience the unruly mind so let me do
this practice let me do this reflection
let me double down this way let me all
while overlooking the root intention
behind all of that that you want to do
it's oh I really resist this unruliness
I really dislike it I crave for it to go
away and that's already a wrong message
you're conveying to the mind
that's why there is no communication yet
or very
little so when the mind is unruly you
have to recognize it as an unruly mind
how saatana describe
it so okay today dog is very susceptible
to mind
instructions he listens I don't even
have to tell it twice so other day like
I'm a
stranger but either way if I get
frustrated or related I will lose the
sight of where the communication takes
place so on the days when it doesn't
listen I have to recognize okay yes it
would have been great if we contined
learning at the same Pace like we did
last week but it's not up to me to
decide that so now you have to adapt you
have to pick the signs and features of
the mind not tailored it how you want it
so that you can teach
it so you recognize it's Andre okay
which means it's going to have a a very
U limited amount of messages I can
convey if
any but what do you do when there is an
unruly dog that you're trying to
train well you stop wasting your time
trying to communicate during that period
of time because it's not listening but
at the same time you don't let it run
wild you at least contain
it and wait for it to calm down without
losing sight of it
and when he comes down
then you convey the
message so it's kind of yes you're
training the
Animal by training yourself really in
regard to
it by recognizing hold on but I can't be
holding this
attitude if I want to train a dog I have
to abandon this I have to upgrade this I
have to change I can't like this is the
message it's getting doesn't matter what
I say on top of it if I'm frustrated if
I'm trying to get rid of it that is the
vibe it's picking from me even if that's
not what I really believe I want that is
what I
do and that's what the animal is going
to
see so that's why I keep saying to
people it's important because if you
assume this external view that saying no
to everything is always
better then you're not going to see this
this whole field of development that's
kind of in between because every time
there is the unruly mind anytime there
is a resistance comes up from your end
you just double down there and say no to
more things so that this won't happen
but it's almost like yeah it's kind of
still carries a certain
implications not necessarily of the
full-blown syab parasa but it has
certain like a same principle of that
magical kind of okay so if I do better
in these other ways this won't come up
because there is a grain of Truth in
that like you could review your behavior
and see is the Mind
unruly because I've been
careless and it's if the answer is no or
there's nothing obvious that you know of
then it's probably not then it's unruly
because he still needs time to
learn but your frustration you're
doubling down you're trying to really
speed it up well that's not going to
help that's going to slow it down
same like your your strings were too
loose you you tighten
them you start tightening them you reach
the kind of right tune and then you
think well tightening brought the right
tune so let me therefore tighten even
more and then you lose the right
un tiing is the thing to do exactly so
if I do tightening because tightening
factually brought the right
tune but only because things were too
loose but now the point comes where
tightening takes you away from the
tun so like for example you
have you think like oh I have a good sex
shame or whatever example you want to
take and then you
feel you feel
bad because you had like
a seemingly conceited thought of
yourself oh have such a good sense of
Shame a very good
smile and then he like no no and then
you start hating yourself you start self
floating it what
it what
happens when you're self
load how does that come to
be what is
soflo can you really load
yourself no yet there is self
no yet there is self
loading so how
come who's loading
who going to say is it just another form
of resisting the mind being unemp
but no you have plenty of resistances
but they don't NE me yourself load
you're not hting
yourself where is the loading come from
all the same place that the kind of self
congratula came from which
is the animal yeah
theal so the animal hates
you and when he
does you ask
yourself is it because of something I've
done as in have I really acted in an
intentionally un Wholesome Way so when
the Mind turned against me he has every
right to do
so but then as I said if you're
established in
virtue sense restraint not even like
perfect perfect you're going to have
your mind loading you without you having
done anything
wrong but at some
it's unpleasant to have your own mind
basically loading it and uh not seeing
that you're experiencing self loading to
put it that way yet it's not you who is
loading yourself it's you who is taking
the mind of the face value of loading
you and that's that's that deeply
ingrained resistance that it's like you can know
resistance that it's like you can know
that you haven't done anything
wrong the Mind still feels the same
towards you at least for that period of
time and you still feel valid yeah okay
so I have to change
this you feel valid uh validated in
those efforts and acceptance of that
loading cuz if you have like a
sense of self praising or self
congratulation that's also from my mind
it's also from mind you're jumping on
that and for the same reason
yeah oh wow I'm so amazing the thought
comes up prompted by the animal for
whatever reason and it's like okay factually it
reason and it's like okay factually it
might be true there and then because of
something I've done or because I've done
nothing to mind just either way way it's
not up to me to take it at a face value
and run with it try blindly accepting it
or blindly resisting it so the point is
even if you're doing everything right in
terms of the gradual
training there will be some
overlap that you would have to grind
through in a sense of overlap that
you're doing everything right yet the
mind is still loading you for whatever
reason whatever day for however long
and it's instead of oh but what let me
change my behavior let me improve it let
me this if you already know that it's
nothing it's not because of anything
obvious that you've done then it's like
no it's just the Mind needs to get the
message that I'm not following along
with this anymore without trying to kill
it beat it strangle it because obviously
that's giving it too much of a
message cuz yeah the dog might just hate
you on some
days and it's like oh I haven't done
anything even accidentally let alone
intentionally so okay you just have to
live through that and calm down the
animal and then
continue but obviously people not seeing
the signs of their own mind not seeing
their own mind whatever happens in their
mind it's their it's there doing it
although see nobody wants to load
themselves nobody can load themselves in
that sense yet they are cu the mind is
and they're fully identified with it
because they don't see anything in
between so then whichever kind of
whimsical direction that animal takes
that's yours it's you doing it why I
don't even know I don't want it yet I'm
doing it and I can't stop
it and that's why pretty much why
meditation is what it is today
contemporarily speaking because you know
as I said there is there there is no
development whatsoever to begin with and
then all people left with is just okay I
can't cope with this anymore so let me
just find ways of dumbing it all down
completely sort of Hing half asleep stop
thinking stop everything just to
experience some form of artificial
piece where I become unaware of the
animal that hates me that I'm identified
with or you could reason and go through
the motions of psychologization and just
repeated steps why and no and why it's why it is
steps why and no and why it's why it is
why it isn't why it shouldn't be why all
all rooted in yeah but see hold on why
do I need to do anything when kind of
this animal being an
idiot it's like I don't so I have to
draw line for myself to stop kind of
giving into that okay
this and if he loves you
fine it's not fine if he load you
because you did something
stupid but then you'll know that very
clearly that's again that sense of Shame
will be very very obvious if it was
broken but yeah if you take the mind at
face value it will present you with
completely faultless blameless scenarios
and blame you for it and you'll feel the
guilt irrational guilt you'll feel it
and if you think okay so every this
every guilt must be dealt
with you're falling for its
trap so the more familiar you are
with the mind doing
that yeah the better but the familiarity
of the mind doing that is not on the
level of theory and reasoning yes you
need to learn about it but really
familiarity is through not acting out of
no matter what the Mind presses you with
you're becoming more and more accustomed
to more and more
familiar more and more like uh wise in
that sense because the sutas I think it's
sense because the sutas I think it's
Thea they said wisdom is the absence of
this passion basically absence of
passion oh sorry depence of passion yeah
so The Disappearance of passion equals
wisdom not having it all fit in your
little mind like you know all the
theories and stuff it's all nice and
connected it matches every suit like no
no and you realize you could be telling
yourself all the right answers and they
will not bring this passion if however
you don't bother with any answering for
whatever reason but you do not give in
to an unruly animal doesn't matter what
it pressures you doesn't matter how
personally it tries to get you are
developing this passion because that's
the the essence of this passion is not
acting out of the passionate mind and
developing wisdom at the same time well
that's what wisdom is
yeah so yeah by all means become
familiar with
it through not acting out and through
recognizing the peripheral mental States
the moods that animal is in the pressure
moods that animal is in the pressure
that it exerts on you something subtle
sometimes coarse either way you see it
is like okay losing sight of
this in other words like forgetting
about it is how I make the mistake of
sort of going along with it but if I
don't lose a sight of it whatever is
revolving around it's still not a
problem it still hasn't taken the Senter
stage as you spoke
before that taking that uh
that uh
movement of the mind for granted as
yours your point of
view because that has enormous
consequences over that's basically how
THS out really but um yeah but like like
an example I was thinking about recently
reminded me
um like um long time ago somebody I was
speaking to with in the place where I
was before
um we were having a conversation and she
said you know like I I think I I really
started thinking about what it would be
like to experience
nonself and to experience complete
dispassion and I realized I'm terrified
of it I don't want I don't want it she
got the right right idea yes and that
was the point and she felt fear yeah but
then she said so I don't want it I don't
know what to do I think I just and then
she said and and I and she literally
like blocked that was okay so I have to
try and make myself wanted in order to
then practice for
it and I was thinking like and I
remember thinking at the time that's
very because I had recognized I loads of
times like thinking about it and feeling
fear like I'm terrified of becoming an
arant I don't want to but then I would
think why should I take that at face
value face value why should I take that
as the measure as the reference point
for what is good when does what I want
when has what I want doing what I want
to do
brought happiness and Lasting peace it
hasn't so you end up realizing oh
actually this is the only way I have to
do it in spite of at the same time
recognizing oh I don't want to the the
mind doesn't want to
yeah
but and even like just basic sense of
Shame as kind of can kind of help with
that in a way as because you know just
that would kind of put a block like I
think about you know I don't want to so
maybe I'll just like abandon it and you
feel a sense of Shame no like no it's
not a right right thing to it's not a
right thing to do I don't want to quit
like I can't I can't let myself just
quit like you know or like you know
other people The Bu people in the
Buddhist time all these people you see
they were struggling so on if they could
do it I must be able to do too there
just these Bas that's the difference
between sort of doing it already for the
more transparent authentic reasons as
opposed to doing it just because you
were inspired on a kind of wrong idea
yeah yeah I think I was saying before
like even when I was so I was I wanted
to become Monk and I was already
prepared writing to the monasteries and
stuff and then I had that interview for
the UK Visa pretty much the only place
that replied to me and they denied me
okay I went there and I went for and he
said sorry like you know if you were
already a monk or something I could let
you in because that's the category but a
non member of religious order to go to
become a member of religious order I
can't give you the member of religious
order Visa because it's simply not true
and I remember I was relieved yeah I was
going home feeling like oh weight's off
me now cuz I genuinely
tried and then I remember I was scared
after that thought because I thought oh
so then like if I'm relieved means
I have to like fight now twice as hard
to not slide back cuz before at least I
had something that was sort of heading
to
words and then like three or four days
and he called me said come on I found
the category I can slot you in and then
he was like back on that that okay we're
doing this but yeah if I were to just
let my mind decide I would not have done
it I had no reason to do it like there
was nothing that I was running away from
or bothering quite the opposite but deep
down you realize yeah but how long will
these things last how long will before
it changes the way I don't want it to
change and it's like it's like an
obvious truth it's right there it's like
oh yeah like nothing else is really
worth um but if if say if your practice
is just rooted in that
inspiration which it might be fine in
the beginning like that's the only way
you know but you will come to the point
where exactly you realize the mind
doesn't want it and if you still use
your insiration as a as a criteria for
making a judgment of right and wrong
you're done yeah then you'll be hopping
from one practice to another one place
to another this that and then whatever
takes you fancy which usually is going
to be non practice non virtue and
sensuality and so
on so it's
like that's why like you really like
through correct recollection reflection
and Drilling in this contexts you are
clarifying stuffff um um so even when the mind
stuffff um um so even when the mind
doesn't want to do it the broader
picture still kind of does not sort of
sway because of it it's like yeah he
doesn't want to do it but what else is
there to do other than tame your mind
rightly because whatever I would let my
mind decide to do it's because it wants
the peace he wants the happiness he just
obviously doesn't know how to get it in
that uh wise way you would go ignorantly
about it so if I allow it to go in
ignorant ways about those seeking those
things like I'm the one who's going to
suffer and the mind will
suffer so but that perspective like yes
it makes sense you can read it you can
hear it you can understand it you can
even believe in it but you need to be
you know maintaining that to really sink
in so then when the Mind does become
unruly becomes like this becomes like
that the this practice has weight the
perspective sorry has weight has
value um because was yeah it's just
um Hollow words really empty
ideas I've thought of um like the the
virtue of like the right kind of
stubbornness Almost sure if it's applied
rightly yes yeah just
like stubbornness in the against your
own mind's tides
but it is that movement of the Mind
movement of the
animal when it sort of
Twitches calls
away it's like you can't help but
Overlook it even if you see it you can't help but
it even if you see it you can't help but
Overlook
it and by that I mean you can't help but
be identify with it first take it for
granted and then okay this is the animal
once you already that's like oh hold on
doesn't matter the movement it belongs
to the
animal so it's maintaining that
perspective not acting out and becoming
more and more familiar with these
movements of the animal and then one day
you just realize oh it moved and I
haven't identified myself with it
it's not like something you can pre
decide when it's going to when you're
not going to be identified but if you
keep recognizing that yes the re the
sole reason I am feeling the pressure of the
reason I am feeling the pressure of the
animal uh although I'm not making it
worse or aggravating it through acting
out the fact that I am being pressured
to act out means it's some somewhere
underneath that
way I have taken it up I am identified
with
it but it's not something you can just
travel back undo that part and then
everything else fall to place you can
only do it in reverse so to speak so
you're doing it more accurately not by
trying not to take up the movement
through your
reasoning no you're doing it more
accurately through not giving into the
pressure and conveying that message to
the mind so then the more it moves in the
mind so then the more it moves in the
face of that clear message the clearer
the movement becomes as if something
that it's not you're doing doesn't
matter which way it
goes and that it cannot touch you that's
the point basically you Flinch the
animal does that to your face and you
Flinch and you just can't it's like a
reflex but you realize the only reason
you still have that reflex is because
you still are not 100% clear that it
cannot touch you doesn't matter how
forcefully it comes at you
but the clearer that becomes the less of
a Flinch you're going to have so the
Mind moves quickly it makes no
difference to you because it moves
elsewhere it is elsewhere before it
moved and its movement remains elsewhere
not where where it can they can harm you
exactly like by not
flinching you have your eyes wide open
you can see the whole thing clearly and
you recogn actually cannot touch but
it's like well the recognition of you
cannot be touched starts way before you
you you're able to not flinch you'll be
flinching but through not acting out
through recognizing that pressure
although you flinched you recognize but
hold on it still cannot do anything
unless I act out of it that's how it
starts to sink in and comes to the point
of where even the Split Second animal
twitch does not make you
Flinch cannot make can Flinch not cuz
you're so focused on it to not flinch
and prop your eyes open or something
it's not a it's not a it's not rooted in
like determination it's rooted in
just understanding sinking deep enough
whereby doesn't matter how quick how
sudden how spontaneous how unexpected
the movement of the animal is there is
absolutely no wavering in the
understanding that you're
untouchable by that movement and
everything else second to
it cuz that's the sole reason you
wouldn't be
flinching the understanding that it
cannot touch you is deep enough it has
settled in far enough and that's the
sole reason you would be
flinching is if you
still at some point at some corner of
your mind are unsure whether it's going
to touch you or not whe it's going to
hurt you or not and then you flinch
and getting getting to that point is
just like you said you can't you can't
start down the r I'm saying like what
you should be aiming for but yeah don't
fall into view now okay so let me learn
how not to Flinch while it's still
acting giv to the pressure of that's
already the result of the Flinch so it's
like you'll come to that point if you
would have been taming the mind rightly
it's just as I said you're training
yourself as well in recognizing how far
the animal can go
and goes the same way when the Mind
twitches and
jumps and moves towards pleasure you
Flinch it's not only when he turns
against you sensuality is a Flinch
already you're affected by it because
you flinched you were like
oh it moved the animal kicked and I
flinched and now I'm running with
it so I got to stop running
now I have to endure
the kicking in my face put up with
flinching until it I really understand
that it cannot harm me then the animal
will start to understand and give up
trying to kick me CU it
works it doesn't need to hit you it just
needs you to move to move so by by by
kind of twitching towards you you Flinch
and you moved it doesn't
he doesn't need to make a
contact but once you stop moving because
you fully
understood that the Mind cannot touch
you well then the mind will eventually
give up trying to touch you because it
also understood that the threat of
touching you doesn't work anymore
because you are not
flinching and that's why it needs to be
done in reverse
because there's a lot riding
on top of that Flinch layers upon layers
upon layers of you just proliferating
and building up perceptions to the point
of say mind gets gets a sudden desire
you Flinch like momentarily you blink
let's say that that way you open your
eyes next Second and next thing you see
it's You full on riding towards
it there's nothing else in between
basically that's just like General untrained mind
that's just like General untrained mind
like
sensuality comes to your
face you Flinch as I said eyes are
closed for a millisecond when you open
them you are already 80% down down the
rabbit hole of
sensuality because yeah there's a lot
packed in that Split Second that's the
whole undoing um on the on the level of the
undoing um on the on the level of the
middle way the gradual
training so first and and foremost you
simply stop acting out that's still now
you have to bear the whole weight of the
threatening animal trying to move you
desire hindrances you flinching I you
being affected by it but not making it
worse through not making it
worse your perspective broadens you do
okay yes it still touches me I would
really like to not be even touched cuz
that would be even more peaceful but
it's nowhere near me just running down
in fullon panic mode or sensual mode or
anger mode and acting out like a maniac
which then makes the animal even more
powerful um and as you keep as I
said uh progressing in in the reverse of
the direction of your
proliferation the point comes when even
if the animal flinches flinches because
it's kind of uh in face of death and its
last breath or being killed you won't be
moved by you won't Flinch on that even
if the animal twitches and fights for
its life you won't be moved by that
that's why Aran cannot be touched by
death either he's free from
it doesn't matter what animal does how
close it feels you know it always going
to stop in front of your feet cannot
possibly come closer impossible because
again you haven't reasoned it or just
believe in it you've been doing it and
it's been confirmed over and over and
over and over and over again even the
dumbest of the mind will understand it
it will have to sink
in and that's the differences in the
sutas yes somebody needs to do this for
a fortnite and he's an AR need to for
seven years but either way even the
dumbest of the minds will have to get
the message if you stick to that right
level